And here was the game changer. He says,
"People who are interested come up with
stories, reasons, and excuses all the
time about why they can't or why it
can't be done. And people who are
committed upgrade their identity and
their beliefs to match the destiny they
want. And then they level up their
skills and habits to take the action
required to achieve every one of their
goals.
>> Markets, speculation, [music] and risk.
This is the Chat with Traders podcast.
[music]
Thank you for tuning in [music] to
episode 317 of the Chat with Traders
podcast. This is Tessa, your co-host,
and we've got a great episode for you
today. As traders, we're familiar with
back testing strategies, aren't we? But
the part of trading nobody can really
back test is your brain. And if you've
ever said, "I know what to do and still
didn't do it, this one's for you."
Today, my co-host Ian chats with our
guest John Asarf, one of the leading
behavioral performance and mindset
experts in the world. He's a serial
entrepreneur who has built five
multi-million dollar companies,
including growing a real estate
franchise to over four billion in annual
real estate sales and co-founded a tech
company that went public on NASDAQ with
a peak market capitalization in the
billions. He's the founder and CEO of
Neuro Gym, a neuroscience-based company
dedicated to helping people retrain
their brains for success, and the author
of multiple books that have become New
York Times bestsellers. Some listeners
may also recognize John from his
appearance in The Secret, where his work
reached a much broader audience. Now,
today's episode is not really about
markets, but it's more about
performance. Because whether you're
trading, building a business, or trying
to break a pattern that keeps showing
up, the real bottleneck, it's the part
of the brain designed to protect
certainty, comfort, and identity, even
when those very things are holding us
back. John has a powerful origin story
from growing up in scarcity and chaos to
a defining moment at 19 years old when a
mentor asked him a question that
completely changed the direction of his
life. And you'll hear that question soon
enough in the interview. In this
conversation, we also talk about why
willpower alone fails, why people keep
snapping back to familiar results, and
what actually needs to change for new
behaviors to stick. And there's so much
more. If you've ever felt capable of
more but keep reverting to the same
outcomes, this conversation will land.
To me, this is one of those episodes
where you will want to listen to at
least twice. So, without further ado,
ladies and gentlemen, we're so pleased
to present John Asarf.
>> Well, John, I'd like to uh welcome you
to uh Chat with Traders.
>> Thank you, Ian. Great to be with you.
>> You've had quite a fascinating story. uh
from the streets to building
multi-million dollar companies. Can you
briefly take us back to where you grew
up and the beliefs about wealth that you
absorbed in that environment?
>> Uh sure. I uh I was born in Israel and
then when I was five, my parents were
tired of wars and so they decided to
move my brother and sister and I and
them to Montreal, Canada. And um in
Montreal I I I fell uh two years behind
because I didn't speak English going
into grade one. And so I fell at two
years behind. Um felt like I wasn't good
enough or smart enough. That was a a
rambunctious, energetic kid and I
thought I just wasn't, you know, wasn't
smart enough. So I got into a lot of
trouble as a kid. And my father was a
cab driver trying to make it in a new
city. Unfortunately, he was an alcoholic
and a gambler. So at the end of every
day, he usually owed people money cuz he
was at the horse races losing money or
playing cards and losing money and then
drinking and then coming home. And so it
created a very very uh tumultuous
relationship between my parents and a
very very challenging one for me because
he would take on some of his anger with
his fists and legs uh on me as a kid
because I was getting into trouble. So
money was scarce. um he did illegal
things when he was younger and um I was
taught that in order to succeed in life,
you've got to screw other people um you
know to get ahead. And when I was in my
teens, I got involved in a small street
gang and we did breaking and entries and
I sold drugs and I did inhale, I did
sell them, I did sniff them, I did do
everything with them. So, I was guilty
as charged um on several occasions. And
that was really my upbringing, you know,
and uh I I spent a lot of time on the
streets with people that were um mini
hoodlams. We didn't have guns back then.
We had knives and numchucks. Um we were
all into martial arts to protect
ourselves from the fights we would get
into and we had to be protected when we
were doing illegal things. And uh that
was, you know, 12 to 19 years young. And
I got in trouble with the law, detention
centers, the whole works. But I remember
specifically, you know, the the
discussion around money was that wealthy
people lie, steal, and cheat to make it.
Money was scarce. Um, and um, it wasn't
reserved for my family or me. And that
was kind of like the beginning of my
belief system. And then uh my brother
who was concerned for my safety um had a
a gentleman by the name of Allan Brown
that he taught tennis to. My brother was
a tennis coach and he asked Alan Brown
if he'd at least talk to me to try and
knock some cents into me and maybe maybe
even offer me a job. And at the time I
was working for Philips Electronics in
their shipping department, making a $165
an hour. Um you know, opening boxes,
closing boxes, and I hated it. And so I
took the train from Montreal to Toronto
to meet this man for lunch. And at lunch
he asked me a whole bunch of questions.
But the the thing that transitioned and
transformed my life. There was one man,
one question, one answer transformed my
life. I was sitting at lunch with him.
It was like 12:30 in the afternoon. Um
and um he he asked me what were my
goals. And I said, "Well, I'd like to
get a better job. I'd like to buy a car.
I'd like to move out of my parents
house." And he says, "Well, that's all
nice and dandy." He said, "But um don't
you have any bigger goals?" I said,
"Nope." So, I remember he he uh Ian, he
he he reached into his briefcase. He
took out this document and it was a goal
setting guide. And the first question,
he asked me if I would answer. I said,
"Of course, I'll answer the questions."
The first question was, you know, um uh
at what age do you want to retire?
And I was 19 at the time. And I'm like,
"Retire? I want a job? What do you mean
retire? my father, you know, is in his
40s. He can't retire. So, uh, I said,
"What am I supposed to put here, Mr.
Brown?" He said, "Just pick a number." I
said, "Is is 45 okay?" You know, "Sure,
put it down." The second question,
that's funny, I'm chuckling now. Says,
"Upon retirement, how much net worth do
you want to have?" And so, I said to Mr.
Brown, I said, "Excuse me, what does net
worth mean?" [laughter]
I didn't know. Uh, how much income do
you want to make? And I said, "What am I
supposed to put here?" And he said,
"Well, just put the amount of money you
want." I said, "Is $10,000 a month,
okay?" He go, "Sure, put it down."
Anyway, and he said, "You know, what
kind of car do you want?" I wrote it
down. Mercedes, "What kind of house do
you do you want? Fourbedroom house." And
it just had me writing down this this
answers to questions I'd never
considered around my life and what I
want to have, do, be, and achieve. And
after about 10 minutes, I gave him back
the paper and he looked at it. He goes,
"I mean, this is really good." He said,
"I'm going to ask you one question, and
the answer to this question will
determine whether you achieve every one
of the things you wrote down as answers
on this document."
And as you can imagine, I was thinking
in the back of my head, "Yeah, sure. Uh
uh, one answer to one question." And he
leans in and, um, he he lowered his
voice. He goes, "Son, are you interested
in achieving all of these things
or are you committed to achieving them?"
And I remember like, you know, wanting
to scratch my head like interested or
committed like, "What's the difference?"
I just asked them feeling stupid again.
I said, "Excuse me, Mr. Brown, what
what's the difference?" And here was the
game changer. He says, "People who are
interested come up with stories,
reasons, and excuses all the time about
why they can't or why it can't be done.
And people who are committed upgrade
their identity and their beliefs to
match the destiny they want and then
they level up their skills and habits to
take the action required to achieve
every one of their goals." So he
says,"Now that you know the answer,
which are you?" And he leaned over. I
said, "Well, well, in that case, uh,
sir, I'm committed."
And at 19 years young, this was May
1980, to put into perspective. He
reaches out his hand, puts my hand in
his in that in that case, son, I will be
your mentor. And I said, "Wow." Uh,
thank you, sir. Uh, uh, uh, uh, what's a
mentor?
>> [laughter]
>> that Ian was the beginning of my mindset
shift
to being committed and then he helped me
get my real estate license which I went
to school for five weeks, passed the
test on my own which was a miracle in
itself. Um I started selling real estate
for him and he taught me the skills for
marketing to cold call. Um, and then he
taught me the skills for doing these
things called for sale by owners. And
six months later, working every day
diligently with his toutelage,
I made my first 10,000 in a month.
>> Wow, that's a lot of money back then.
>> At the it was a lot. And my father at
the time was making 25,000 a year
>> as a cab driver. So, Mr. Brown gave me a
shift in my perspective,
had me answer the question, interested
or committed, and then he put me in the
environment with the right training to
upgrade my skills and to upgrade my
behaviors.
And then he was able to help me through
the management team track and measure
what I was doing and tweak and adjust
what I was doing until I was locked and
loaded for what it took to make 10,000 a
month. And I've used the exact same
principles with hundreds of thousands of
my students, but also in my in my in my
life over the last 45 years. I built one
company at four and a half billion
dollars a year. Another company was
worth two and a half billion dollars on
NASDAQ because I took it public. Um but
I used that same thinking interested or
committed and then reverse engineered
the identity, the beliefs and the
strategies to achieve the success. So
from there we can get into anywhere you
want. in this day where information uh
is readily available to everybody uh on
their phones and most people would say,
"Hey, that sounds uh great, sounds
logical." Um why is it that people can
uh agree with this and yet when it comes
to actually putting it into practice? Do
people lack uh enough willpower or
what's kind of
>> Great question. Um the area that I've
specialized in the last 45 years is
behavioral neuroscience and really
understanding the neuroscience and the
mechanism by which we not just set goals
but achieve goals. Just give you an
example. When you and I or anybody else
that might be listening to us say that
sounds great. You know I'm going to be
committed and I'm going to set a goal to
make $10,000 a month or an hour or a day
or whatever the case is and I'm
committed. Um what we know is that
happens in the preffrontal cortex part
of the brain a part of the brain right
that can make decisions and even imagine
that [clears throat] I I'm going to
achieve it. So we can we can do that but
there's another part of the brain called
the basil ganglia and that's where the
habits reside of what we're used to
thinking and doing is now just because I
make a decision to want to achieve a
goal doesn't mean that that gets
translated into the behaviors the
thinking the emotions required to
actually follow through with new
actions. So what happens is most people
don't understand that whatever you're
earning now, let's say we're talking
about money, whether you're investing in
the stock market or making x amount of
money at work or in your business,
everybody has something that um we know
is a financial set point, a current
financial set point. And it works like a
thermostat does on, you know, in your
home or your car, whatever the setting
is. Okay, that's the system that
regulates, you know, that setting for
homeostasis.
Well, let's say you're making 10 grand a
day or a month, it doesn't matter, and
you want to make 20. Well, if you don't
reset the subconscious settings, then
you might use willpower for today and
tomorrow and the next day, but the
setting will always go back to the
default mode because that's what's easy
and convenient. And there are automatic
patterns in the brain that require
almost zero energy to implement. That's
called automaticity.
And so 95% of our behaviors daytoday are
based on automaticity and automatic
behaviors and thoughts and emotions that
align
with that for our comfort zone. And
that's why a lot of people, especially,
you know, New Year's resolution people,
okay, you know, they they have these New
Year's resolutions, they're motivated,
they're excited, they take the actions,
but we know from behavioral
neuroscience, it takes uh 14 days to
develop a new pattern in the brain. But
it takes between 66 days and and 180
days for that pattern to be reinforced
enough to override the old automatic
patterns. So most people don't have the
right process. They have the right uh
motivation. They have the right desire.
They have the right um reasons why they
want to. But most people have never been
taught how do I create and reinforce a
habit that matches with the income that
I want to make. And we just launched for
example our neuro fitness platform and
all of my students have to agree to at
least training their brain or retraining
their brain for a 100 days so that we
have a real shot of the behavior
sustaining itself. So we need to use
willpower on the front end, but we also
need to do some other things to
reinforce the the neural patterns. And
most people just have the process wrong
um and they don't have the skill for it.
>> So are you talking about a lot of people
um know of the conscious and the
unconscious mind? Are you referring to
the unconscious mind? Uh and do our bad
habits
uh reside there?
Yeah. So, let's go to conscious and
either subconscious or non-concious.
We don't want to go to unconscious
because that's when we're like knocked
out. So, the the term is really
conscious or non-concious. We're not
aware of it or subconscious. So, yes,
all of our implicit beliefs, all of our
habits, our identity, all of our
emotions are triggered in the
subconscious based on the meaning we
have in long-term memory. So yes, that
is the part of your brain that you were
not born with your subconscious wired.
It's called right. So we have potential,
but you weren't born with an identity.
You weren't born with beliefs. You
weren't born with fears. You weren't
born with any skills.
And so anything that we repeat that's
empowering or disempowering, positive or
negative, constructive or destructive
becomes wired or softwired in the
subconscious mind. So the art of wanting
to earn more income is really no
different than the art of wanting to
lose 20 pounds and keep it off. Yes, we
have to have the right diet. Yes, we
have to have maybe some exercise or you
know thermogenic activity. Um, and yes,
we have to um maintain that new pattern
of releasing the weight or making more
money, but making the behavior that gets
us the results we want more permanent.
And so that just takes some uh creation
and reinforcement of new patterns in the
brain. You know, when I work with with
my clients, uh, and I've got clients
who've gone from zero to a billion a
year, okay, in revenue in their
companies and hundreds of millions and
tens of millions, and the first thing we
do is say, okay, what would be the
identity
of somebody who's already earning that
amount of money?
>> What's the identity? Right? Because you
and I have an identity and it's
supported by beliefs,
right? and it's supported by our uh
facts and supported by a whole host of
associations and a whole host of
references. But if we said, okay, you
want to make X amount of money, the type
of person who makes that amount of
money, what is she like? What are his
character traits? What are his habits?
What does he believe?
And we make a list. Okay? Almost like if
you were making a list to create an
identity for a Hollywood character, you
want to create a list with as much
detail as possible. So, first we say
here is the objective, the the income.
Here's the identity. Here are the
beliefs, okay, that this person has
about his or her ability to earn money,
manage money, invest, protect, get out
of debt, or use debt as leverage. The
five pillars of financial success. here
are the habits that this person has and
the behaviors that this person
consistently does. So we map out what
that is and then we ask ourel this
question. How do I embody these traits
so that the income I want to generate
is in resonance with my new identity and
beliefs and habits.
And most people leave that part out. And
that's why most people are stuck at
earning whatever they earn per month,
per day, per year, etc. Most people
don't go from making 100,000 to a
million. Most people do not.
>> Well, why is that? Do they believe that
uh it's not possible? Like it's asking
too much? Are there things in the subcon
subconscious that they're unaware of
that sabotage uh their efforts? There's
um there's
>> Are you ready to get serious about
trading? Then join Tasty Trade,
Investopedia's best platform for options
trading in 2026. Stocks, options,
futures, and more. Tasty Trade has
everything you trade all in one
platform. Get low commissions, including
zero commission on stocks, so you can
keep more of what you earn. Tasty Trade
is packed with advanced charting tools,
back testing, a pre-built strategy
selector, risk analysis tools, and more
features to help you trade smarter. See
equities and derivatives with high
trading volumes, dividends, upcoming
earnings reports, and more with their
pre-built watch lists. Or create a
custom watch list to keep an eye on the
companies and sectors that matter to
you. Manage your positions with speed
and precision using active trader mode,
one-click trading, and smart order
tracking. Plus, Tasty Trade's stellar
trade desk team offers live support
during trading hours if you need it.
Visit tastyrade.com/hat
for more info. Tastyrade, Inc. is a
registered broker, dealer, and member of
FINRA, NFA, and SIPC.
>> Four things that get into people's ways.
So number one is uh and again we're
going to get into a little bit of the
neuromchanics of what happens in the
brain. And if we're going to talk about
the brain which is my my passion uh
let's first understand this fact. Every
brain functionally works the same.
Every brain functionally works the same.
Like every gas car functionally works
the same. Every electrical car
functionally works same. Every bicycle
functionally works same. Every brain
functionally works the same. So that's
fact number one. So when we're talking
about what would prevent me from
achieving the goal that I have? And so
the first thing I say is uh is there
more than enough money in the world? And
most people would say, well, of course
there is. There's more than enough
money, assets, gold, you know, crypto,
whatever you want to call it. Um stocks,
bonds, uh uh silver, etc. that represent
money. So the the problem is not that
there's not enough, there's more than
enough. So now let's find out, you know,
what could be preventing me from having
more than enough, the amount I want. So
number one, when somebody doesn't know
how to achieve the income goal they
want, they have a lot of self-doubt. I
doubt my ability because I don't know
how to. So I have self-doubt, which also
puts me in a state of uncertainty.
In a state of uncertainty, the
motivational circuit in the brain shuts
off. Why? Because our brain is naturally
wired for safety and survival first and
for avoidance of being embarrassed,
ashamed, ridiculed, judged, rejected or
failing.
So in the absence of knowhow, we revert
back to safety and comfort doing what we
know. Number one. Number two,
what if
going after the income that I want,
whether it's through investments or or
any, you know, any other type of mean,
what if there's a chance I will lose my
money? What if there's a chance I will
fail? What if there's a chance I make
the wrong decisions? What will that do
to my self-image, my self-worth, my
self-esteem? What will that do to my
lifestyle? What would that do putting me
behind the APA? What would it do to pay
my mortgage, my car, my house payment to
my wife, my kids? So, our brain is
consistently
preventing, it's predicting first what
potential outcomes are. If there is a
potential negative outcome,
it puts the break on behavior. And
that's because we haven't learned how to
regulate the emotion of fear or being
embarrassed or ashamed or ridiculed,
judged or rejected or failing. So the
issue is not failing. The issue is the
meaning we have around failing. The
issue is the meaning that my brain is
projecting of what might happen if I
don't succeed or I succeed and fail. So
it's projecting into the future what
might happen, but it's feeling the
emotion in the present moment that shuts
down the motivational circuit or
behavioral cortex. So now we're at two
Um, so then, um, can't we just use our
logical mind, uh, to, um, it sounds like
it's almost like a battle between our
logical mind and and our, uh,
subconscious mind, which generates this
fear. Can't we just, uh, have a nice
little discussion uh, with the two sides
of the brain and and use our logical
mind to persuade the subconscious to go
along?
Unfortunately, you use your conscious
mind to understand
what is happening. So yes, we can use um
behind me, I know most nobody can see,
but I have uh above me over my left
show, I have the Einstein image and a
painting and to the right of me, I have
Frankenstein's monster. These represent
two different parts of the human brain.
Uh it's both part of the prefrontal
cortex. So one part makes a decision
what I want. It can imagine you know
success. It can imagine the lifestyle.
It can imagine the charities. It can
imagine the cars, the house, the dreams
and all that stuff. But right next to
the left prefrontal cortex there is the
brain's protector and that is Frankie's
monster I call it. And that part of the
brain is overriding the goal desiring
mind with the lyic system, emotional
mind that's there for safety and
protection and survival. So can you be
aware that you keep sabotaging your
success? Can you be aware you keep
procrastinating? Yes. And then the next
layer of that is what is it that I am
actually trying to protect? So you can
use your logical smart brain to
understand the situation and then with
some techniques I call them inner size
techniques you can actually shift these
subconscious patterns that are running
autopilot for protection. So absolutely
and you can do that and this is where
you want to create some daily inner
sizes once you're aware of that
situation. So, so far we have um uh
fear, we have um lack of knowledge and
skills, we have beliefs that may be
limiting us, you know, and so you say I
want to earn X, but then but I can't
because and so now we start using you
know stories and reasons and excuses
based on what we believe. And so in the
brain there's two types of beliefs and
most people don't know this. The first
one is called an explicit belief. It's a
belief to say, well, I believe I can
earn that.
But there's an implicit belief in the
subconscious mind that might also say,
but you don't know how to um in the past
when you've tried, okay, you failed or
when your dad did this or mother did
this or friend did this or the other
person who invests did this, they
failed. So, we can have opposing
beliefs. We can have beliefs that we say
we believe. But if our subconscious
belief, the implicit belief is that I'm
too young or too old, it's not the right
time, I don't have enough skill, I don't
have enough knowledge, uh whatever
reason we have is stronger than the
reason why we must, our limiting beliefs
will hold us back.
Hence that's the is that the importance
of making the commitment like you talk
about because does that help to uh help
our conscious mind to override the
limiting beliefs uh of the subconscious?
>> Well, just because we're committed
doesn't mean we override the
subconscious minds. But because we're
committed then we will shift into a
state of awareness of what's happening.
I'm not taking action. I have it on my
calendar and schedule to do this and I
keep procrastinating. I keep
self-sabotaging.
Now, when we're committed, we go, okay,
I understand something is blocking me.
Now, let me go deeper than, you know,
something is blocking me. What could be
blocking me? So, yes, we can start using
commitment and a reason why we must
achieve the success has to be bigger
than the reasons why we're not. Let me
repeat that. The reason why we must
commitment must be bigger than the fear
must be bigger than the limiting belief
must be bigger than the fourth thing
which is my self-image
and my identity. So some people have a
goal of what they want to achieve but
they have a hidden self-image
that does not believe they deserve it.
or they don't believe, okay, that
they're ready for it because of their
self-image.
So, it's either worthiness, deserving,
or timing.
So, any one of these subconscious
reasons with knowledge and skills being
both conscious and subconscious can hold
us back and dead in our tracks before we
even take action. So yes, we want to set
the vision. Yes, we want to set the
goals. Yes, we want to create the
timelines. And then we want to say
what's the identity that I need to
create at the subconscious level. And
what beliefs must I have? What behaviors
must I have? And what habits must I
create that become my automatic way of
being? So a perfect example is this.
Let's say somebody has on their own
earned a million dollars, okay? And
they've they they they've they've done
the work. They've they've done the
trials and the tribulations. Let's say
they lose a million dollars.
They are 10 time actually a hundred
times more likely to make that million
back than somebody who's won a million
dollars in the lottery and lost it. Why?
Because identity.
Somebody who won the lottery doesn't
have the beliefs that they can earn the
amount of money. They might believe they
can win it again.
But whatever patterns have been
reinforced are the patterns that become
automatic. the patterns that become
automatic either are aligned with what
we call a sympathetic resonance with
your vision and goals or you're going to
have an enormous amount of what we call
our destructive interference patterns
preventing you from achieving those
goals. So, you'll create you'll
procrastinate, you'll self-sabotage,
you'll start, you'll stop, you'll you'll
you'll feel energized, you'll take
action, you won't take action, and it'll
be all over the place. And we all behave
almost entirely congruently with our
hidden self-image and identity every
single day.
>> So, uh, in the trading world, it's it
can be, uh, fairly common for new
traders to say, "Hey, um, you know, I
don't have any fear of this. I'm I'm
ready to go. I got my account set up. I
got $10,000 in the account, and I'm
ready to turn it into a million this
year, and uh uh I have no fear. Um uh
I'm ready to take on big risk. Uh so
what what part of the brain does that
kind of mentality come from?
>> It comes from the imagination center and
it comes from the ignorant part of the
brain that doesn't know the reality.
Like think about this. Uh how long have
you been in in the field you're in? How
many how many decades?
>> Decades,
>> right? And how many people in those
decades um if we take out the internet
heyday uh we we take out some of the you
know the the uh boom markets in real
estate or in the stock market. How many
people have taken 10,000 turn into a
million that you know of?
>> Uh very very very rarely. Um, however
though, these uh these newer traders
will say, "But I see them on um YouTube
uh flashing their Lamborghinis and and
uh I'm not going to let uh uh fear stop
me."
>> And I and I agree. Right. And so um um
they have an enormous amount of motive
for action. um they are being controlled
by a part of the brain called the
nucleus ccumbent and insula which
actually releases dopamine in
anticipation
that they're going to be able to achieve
that goal. It's almost the same type of
drug mechanism when people fall in love,
right? and they don't see, you know,
some of the stuff that they see later on
or and maybe friends will see like that
guy, you you want to go out with that
guy. Don't you see this, this, and that?
Oh my god, no, he's so amazing. Or that
girl. And then it's only after the
oxytocin burn, okay, is gone. You go,
"Oh my god, how come I didn't see that?"
Because we're actually literally dealing
with a drugged brain. So, a brain that
has, you know, dopamine, uh, serotonin,
oxytocin, I'm going to make this money.
I'm going to get that car, that
Lamborghini, and that person that looks
five times worse than I do, that has
half the IQ that I do, you know, because
they're on YouTube, right? Um, we get
motivated, but it's a false sense of
reality. And and so we're blind,
[clears throat] right? And so, we're
blind. Now what does decades of
experience give you hopefully?
Right?
>> Yeah. Wisdom. Prudence.
>> Wisdom. Wisdom. Right. So wisdom. So you
know the odds of that happening. You
know how to set the vision and the
goals. You know how to look at deals.
You know how to analyze a stock. You
know how to risk manage. You know how to
do that stuff because of experience. And
every once in a while, okay, every once
in a while, you know, I have I think 104
investments in tech stocks right now.
And I got in with a VC fund and I got
three unicorns in that 104. And that's
like if we had one in 104 investments,
we would be like jumping for joy. But
we've had three because of the timing of
the AI era. And so I love an
enthusiastic person but an enthusiastic
person without skill and experience is
dangerous and a skilled person without
enthusiasm is also dangerous. So um we
we want to set the vision, we want to
set the goals, um but we want to create
the the internal okay environment
to allow us to be consistent
with the behaviors required for
predictable if we can get predictable
results
and investing. You know, um I often when
I when I teach people about making money
and we get into the investment modules,
I I tell people I said don't confuse
gambling or speculating with investing
because those are the three uh the three
areas, right? A lot of people gamble,
but they say they're investing. If
you're going to gamble, gamble. Uh if
you're going to be a speculator, you
better have a bunch of knowledge and you
know you're speculating that things are
going to go, you know, in your way. And
there's uh experience that'll teach you
when you're gambling and there's
experience that'll teach you if you're
speculating and experience in am I
investing or not. And there's rules of
the game. And most people don't learn
the rules of the game and confuse those
three investments. And so they make the
same decisions the same way for all
three. And it's especially the young
immature investor that confuses
investing with gambling and speculating.
>> So, uh, what kind of advice would you
give to people who feel fear and they
say, "Well, logically what you're
saying, it all makes sense, but I feel
it in my bones because of past
experiences.
What can people do to uh hopefully
diminish the fear?"
>> Great question. So what we know right is
all fear there's 50 different types of
fears that could be triggered. So let me
give you an example and usually what
you're afraid of is actually not what
you're afraid of right so uh let's say
somebody has a fear of losing their
money
>> right so is it really a fear of losing
your money or is it a deeper meta reason
we call it all right a meta reason so if
I lose my money then and let me take you
down a couple channels what does that
mean about me. So, is it a fear of
losing money that's tied to my identity?
Maybe. Is it a fear of losing money
that's tied to my livelihood? I got to
pay my rent or my car payment or I need
groceries, right? So, I can't afford to
be in that amount of pain because I
don't have an escape plan. So, what is
it that you're actually afraid of? So,
if I'm feeling afraid, the first thing
to do is understand this. When we have
the fear circuit activated, it's called
the amygdala, right? Is because our
brain in the subconscious mind is
associating a negative or painful
experience with the thing that we want
to do. Do I want to invest in this
stock? I want to invest in this real
estate deal. I want to invest in in
blank. Now our brain is operating not
just in the decision-making part of it
but if I make this investment and I lose
it
already has come up with what does that
mean about me and for my life or my kids
or my wife or my husband. So, it's
already projecting, okay, the negative
consequences of that decision. And then
it releases cortisol, the stress
neurochemical into the bloodstream. And
when people feel stress, right, it's
when the demand is exceeding their
current capacity. Let me repeat that.
stress circuit, fear circuit is only
activated when the demand exceeds your
current capacity or the capacity that
you think you're going to need to deal
with the problem.
So, but let's deal with the moment by
moment release of cortisol.
When somebody has doubt, fear, worry,
stress, anxiety, or even panic, that
means that that this circuit is active
in the brain. And we have two main
circuits to be aware of. One is called
the sympathetic nervous system, fight,
flight, freeze. The other is the calm to
response circuit which is our
parasympathetic nervous system. Now in
um my uh Amazon number one bestselling
book called inner size. Let's say I feel
fear. If I think about the fear and I
fear and I and I feel what I think about
then I'm going to keep re-triggering
that circuit. Now, if I just stopped and
I took six slow, deep breaths in through
my nose slowly,
fill up my lungs with air, hold it at
the top for three, two, one, and I
breathe out like I'm breathing out
through a straw. So, I'm focusing my
attention on the airflow coming out of
my mouth like it's coming out through a
straw.
If I just do that six times and stay the
course, keep the focus. In, hold, three,
two, one, out, three, two, one, in, 3,
2, 1, or 5, 4, 3, 2, 1. And if I do that
for six inhales and exhales, I
deactivate deliberately
my sympathetic nervous system. And now I
return on my Einstein brain I talked
about earlier. Because when we're in
this fear state, then the Frankie's
monster part of the brain is active. I
have to turn Frankie off to give
Einstein a chance to be able to do what
I call his inner size number two. And
that's okay. What am I afraid of? That's
called awareness, intention, and then
action. So in a calm state, I can now
say what what exactly am I afraid of?
Well, I'm afraid of making a mistake.
Okay. Uh, what specifically
am I afraid will happen if I make a
mistake? Well, I'm going to lose some or
all of my money. And if I lose some or
all of that money, um, what does that
mean or say about me? Does it mean or
say I'm stupid? I'm not smart. Uh, does
it mean like what like what am I really
trying to pro protect? It's called
metacognition.
And if I can get down to what I'm really
trying to protect, okay, is is is is
making sure that I don't lose all the
money and I get in trouble with my wife,
okay, because she doesn't want me
investing, right? Or, you know, that I
won't have money to pay the mortgage and
that's going to create a whole bunch of
stress. So once I know what is it that
I'm really trying to protect or move
away from then I could say okay is there
a way to do this where I lower my risk
or is there a way to do this and if I've
made a mistake in judgment or timing
which we know happens in the in
investing how can I recover and or still
manage everything so that I'm
comfortable and can I do that? Can I Can
I deal with the end consequence
if it happens? If yes, great. Now we've
just reduced the fear. If no, then we go
back to okay, so what can I do that
won't cause me to have so much stress
that it shuts down, okay, my brain and
my physiology in my body. So now we do
that in a calm state where we can
actually do what you suggested earlier.
Now we have a chance to use our thinking
brain to analyze, synthesize and then
come up with real solutions. But we
cannot do that Ian when we are in that
stress state because we our brain our
brains um become extremely myopic on the
problem on the pain on the fear the
frustration on all that stuff. So this
is called emotional regulation. And when
we learn how to be aware of our
emotions, the energy in motion and now
we are deliberate by upgrading our
skills of what to do when this happens.
Now who's in control? My emotions or me?
>> So that breath work exercise is that uh
an example of what you call in your book
inner size like exercise for our inner
being? Yeah, it's exercise your muscles.
You know, with exercise, you inner size
your brain, your neurom muscles to have
more self-control, more confidence, more
certainty. And and there's, you know,
like 10 main inner sizes. Um, you know,
that I that I should learn like, you
know, when you when you learn how to
drive your car, you learn park, you
learn drive, you learn neutral, you
learn going the highway, you learn going
down the street, you learn turning left,
you learn turning right, you learn
parking. Well, what about learning how
to use your brain better since you own a
hundred billion dollar asset already,
but you don't have the users manual for
it?
>> In uh previous videos you've made, uh
you mentioned that the uh the gorilla
brain wants safety and harmony. Uh so,
uh for us traders, we'd we'd like to
know why does it sometimes choose
self-destructive habits like revenge
trading? uh how would that be
interpreted as harmony by the uh gorilla
brain?
>> Yeah, a lot of times revenge training um
is our brain
uh causing us to behave in ways that are
aligned with our subconscious mind and
what we believe we deserve. That's
called self- sabotaging behavior.
So,
think about think about this. You know,
somebody wins the lottery, five million,
10 million bucks, buy a new house, uh
get a new car, give their friends 20
grand, 50 grand, and all of a sudden
they're 10 million goes to 8 million to
6 million to 9 mill to to 3 million to 2
million. And then most people not aware
of this, 92% of lottery winners lose the
money within five years. Part one, part
two. Um, I think it was 80% of people
who won money and lost it said that
winning the money was one of the worst
experiences of their life. Why? Our
brain has to do a few things for us to
feel normal. One of those things that it
does for us to feel normal is it makes
certain that our outside world of
results matches our internal
expectation points.
I'll give you a different example.
Somebody um wants to lose weight and
they lose weight. They lose 20 30 40 50
pounds. Why do over 90% of the people
put all the weight back when they want
to be healthier, skinnier, feel better,
look? Why do they do why do they put all
the weight back? Is it because they want
to put the weight back? No.
It's because all the internal mechanisms
are wired, their set points are wired to
shift all behavior back to baseline
homeostasis. The best visual I've ever
had, Ian, is just think thermostat. If
you have a room set at 70 degrees and
really hot air comes in, a signal is
sent to the air conditioning unit to
turn the air on, right? Until 70° is
met. If, let's say, you have a room at
70° and really really uh cold air comes
in, right? And the temperature goes down
to 62, well, the signal gets sent to the
to the heater. turn the heat on until 70
is met. It's called a cybernetic
mechanism.
You and I and every other human being,
remember, every brain works the same,
has something called a psycho cybernetic
mechanism. Maxwell Maltz was one of the
first to write about it in his book
called Psycho Cybernetics back in the
70s. And so, we all have these
baselines. And so when people, you know,
let's say, make more money than they're
used to, a lot of times they will self-
sabotage and lose the money over the
next week, month, two months, three
months, four months.
>> In your um in your program, do you have
um any kind of uh questions or tests
that help people uncover these um uh
self-limiting beliefs uh that are is in
their subconscious that they may be
totally unaware of?
>> Yeah. when when people go to um my
neurogim.com my neurogim.com one of the
first things we offer everybody for free
is a neuroitness assessment and in that
neuroitness assessment it gives them two
things number one is what brain type are
you and it gives you a score in one of
the five brain types and then you're
going to get your dominant um you know
brain type and subdominant brain type
but it'll also score your seven core
neurom muscles one of the seven core
neurom muscles for example is your
critical thinking skills and your
decision making process. And if your
critical thinking skills are strong,
great. If they're weak, you're in
trouble, right? If your decision-making
skills are strong, great. If they're
weak, then great. Uh and then uh in our
programs on our neuro fitness platform
uh which we literally just launched with
40 AI coaches in there to coach people
as well is we're going to be creating a
slew of assessments neuro fitness
assessments on on beliefs on habits on
emotions on on on cognition on cognition
speed. So, we literally just launched
this to the world um in the last two
weeks and we're putting the final
touches on it for our massive PR
campaign. So, yes,
>> fantastic.
>> Yeah,
>> fantastic. Um let's touch a little bit
about uh goals. Uh people are so used to
u making New Year's resolutions. Uh it's
in January. uh and uh what are some of
the key things that uh we should know
about um when creating goals and uh and
the problems that arise?
>> 80% of people give up on their goals by
February the 8th that they set January
1st. 80%.
>> Goals
setting happens in the uh preffrontal
cortex part of the brain. um the
imagination part of the brain uh and
it's the part of the brain that chooses
what we want and why.
Goal achieving
happens as a result of the hippocampus
long-term memory and the basil ganglia
and and these are just parts of the
brain that do different things. Just
like you have your hand does a different
thing than your elbow does and your knee
does something different than your ass
does. You have different parts of your
brain. They do different things. And
most people don't think of their brain
the way I want them to think about. I
want you to think about your brain like
you would uh an orchestra, right? You
are the conductor, right? And the
conductor says, "We're going to play
this song." That's the goal. Then the
conductor's job, right, is to get the
different musicians to play in concert,
in harmony, in flow.
And so the question becomes,
do you know how to get your brain in
concert, in harmony, in flow between
your conscious mind setting goals, the
lyic system, emotional mind having the
reasons why I want to achieve and how
phenomenal it's going to be and the
imagination saying this is going to be
epic and phenomenal. Do you know how to
translate the sheets of music to the
other parts of the brain that are
responsible for taking consistent
action? And most people look at me like
deer in headlights because they've never
been taught this. So I'll give you an
example.
Whenever I set a new goal, okay, which I
do first, I start off with the vision of
what is life going to be like when that
goal is achieved. And I write it down.
and I write it down. Uh starting with
this language path, I'm so happy and
grateful for the fact that I have now
achieved the goal of blank. And as a
result of achieving my goal of blank, I
feel this and I'm doing this and I'm
helping this and I'm going here and I'm
experiencing this and I write out a
whole story like a Hollywood script part
one.
Now I have the story and now
how do I become the story? So I'll give
you a visual I take all my clients
through. Let's say somebody um tapped
you on the shoulder because you're at
the gym uh uh you're at uh um a friend's
party. you're at a coffee shop and they
tap you on the shoulder and go, "Hey, um
uh I just read this Hollywood script
uh and it stars uh Sylvester Stallone,
Barbara Stryand, and I don't know,
Russell Crow, I don't know, whatever.
And you would be great for this
fiveminute piece, and they're looking
for somebody just like you. If we give
you this script, and we pay you a
million dollars, will you learn the
script and meet us in Hollywood in six
months to film?" You might be scared. Oh
my god, I'm going to get a chance to act
with all these people. I got this five
minute script. Like what could five
minute script?
What would you do to learn and be that
script?
>> Do whatever it takes my whole life
around.
>> Too nebulous. What would you give me
specifics of what you would do? Oh um I
would practice I mean um integrate it
into my life so that every day uh for a
minimum number of hours per day I'm I'm
doing that uh I'm practicing like it's
my most important thing that I'm going
to do.
>> So would you read it a few times a day?
>> Oh yeah. Read it over and over and over
you know 20 30 times a day. Yeah.
>> You might you might record it and listen
to it. You might get your camera out and
practice the role. You might do research
on the role uh but you'd probably do
something every single day to prime your
brain to train your brain to be the
role. First it would take conscious
effort but then with space repetition
practice makes permanent right and
perfect practice makes perfect. So with
with repetition every day for the first
month maybe two hours a day maybe an
hour a day. The second month maybe half
an hour a day. Maybe the third month
half an hour a day. maybe a little bit
every single day, you'd be firing and
wiring this new script you never saw
before. And you would embody the
identity, the beliefs, the character
traits of the script. So that when the
camera came on is three, two, one, go.
You would need the script because you've
become the script.
The way you develop the identity for the
income you want to make, for the trader
you want to be, for the lifestyle that
comes with it, for the confidence and
the certainty and the personal power is
you practice it and rehearse it in your
mind and in your emotions every single
day. And then you take a little bit of
action every day to practice the roll.
So on my desk, I've been doing this for
45 years. I not only have my exceptional
life blueprint that's 50, let me see, 67
pages long with my entire life in here
with my with pictures of my family, the
life that I'm that I'm living, you know,
in our home, the physique that I have
today versus what I had. But I have it
written out uh all my top goals, my
story of my life that's three pages long
and every day I practice it in private.
So I get praised in public for what I
do. So I think of my life like an
athlete would think of her life. You
practice in private or with other
people. So when it's game time, you're
playing to win.
>> Fantastic. This all sounds very
inspirational. Uh John, I'd like to
thank you for coming on Chat with
Traders.
>> Thank you so much. It's been great
coming on with Traders. And I'll give
everybody a little um a free book called
Innersize Your Way to Success that you
can give everybody as my gift.
>> Fantastic. And how can our listeners uh
reach you?
Uh, first thing they should probably do
is go take the neuropitness assessment
at mynuroggeim.com.
And by the time this airs, uh,
everything will be in place, my
neurogurogim.com. And then I'm on uh,
social media on Instagram and YouTube
and, uh, LinkedIn, etc.
>> Fantastic. Thanks for coming on the
show.
>> Thanks, Ian.
>> By the way, the free copy of the book
that John mentioned can be found in the
show notes of the podcast platform that
you're listening from. or if you have
issues finding it, feel free to email us
at hello@ chatwithtraders.com. Thanks
for listening. Again,
>> you've reached the end of this episode
of Chat with Traders, but rest assured,
there are more episodes loaded with
[music] real market insight and zero
hype on the way soon. So, to stay
updated [music] with each great new
release, subscribe to the podcast in
iTunes. And we'd love it if you'd leave
[music] a rating and review. We'll catch
you next time on Chat with Traders.
>> [music]